<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.5">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2019-01-01T21:30:19-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/</id><title type="html">Boveington Law LLC</title><subtitle>Laurie Boveington, Attorney at Law 330.920.1210</subtitle><entry><title type="html">ESTATE PLANNING 101: The basic documents everyone can use</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2017/08/22/estate-planning-101-the-basic-documents-everyone-can-use.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="ESTATE PLANNING 101: The basic documents everyone can use" /><published>2017-08-22T20:51:31-04:00</published><updated>2017-08-22T20:51:31-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2017/08/22/estate-planning-101-the-basic-documents-everyone-can-use</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2017/08/22/estate-planning-101-the-basic-documents-everyone-can-use.html">&lt;p&gt;Part 2 of a 4-part series&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By Laurie M. Boveington, Attorney at Law&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, know that estate planning is much more than just having a Will. The Will is just the post-death document that instructs the Court and other interested parties how you want your estate distributed. But what about while you’re still living? There are numerous other documents that allow other people to help you in times of need, and still other documents that allow certain types of property to pass outside of a Will, and therefore outside of probate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are the basic estate planning documents, and what they do for you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;LAST WILL AND TESTAMENT: Your Will is the document that takes effect the moment you pass away. It allows you to name the people who will benefit from your estate and in what way, as well as any natural beneficiary you wish to disinherit.  It names someone you trust – your executor – to manage the estate. It generally also requests that the executor be permitted to serve without posting bond, which can be costly depending on the size of your estate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;STATUTORY or DURABLE POWER OF ATTORNEY: A Power of Attorney (POA) is the document that allows someone you trust – your agent – to manage your financial affairs if you are not able to do it for yourself, either because you become mentally incompetent, or you are temporarily unavailable. Your agent can do your banking for you, take care of your investments, sell or purchase real or personal property on your behalf, collect benefits, and much more. At the moment of your death, the POA is automatically revoked and your Will takes over.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;HEALTH CARE POWER OF ATTORNEY: A Health Care Power of Attorney (HCPOA) names someone you trust – again, your agent – to make health care decisions on your behalf if you are not able to make decisions for yourself. They can speak to your doctors and pharmacists, obtain your medical records, hire and fire medical providers, transfer you into and out of medical facilities, authorize treatment, etc. This document is used when you are TEMPORARILY disabled, but are expected to recover.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;LIVING WILL: A Living Will specifies your wishes upon a terminal condition or permanent unconsciousness. It allows you to specify no heroic measures, a Do Not Resuscitate (DNR) order, withdrawal of all treatment except for pain relief and comfort measures, and to allow you to die naturally, with your dignity intact. Your agents, or contacts, will work with your doctors to determine if you may recover or not. Two doctors must agree that you have no hope of recovery before this document takes effect. This document also allows you to specify whether or not you wish to be an organ donor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;JOINT AND SURVIVORSHIP DEED: This deed to real property gives the owners “rights of survivorship” without passing through the probate process. It is especially useful for married couples, but any pair or group of people can execute one. There is specific language that must be used, otherwise it is an ordinary deed with two or more owners, called “tenants in common,” and when one of them passes away, the other(s) will need to probate the house in order to transfer the title.  It is important to note that whomever takes ownership of the real property takes it subject to any mortgage or other encumbrance. When one of the survivorship owners dies, the other(s) need only execute an affidavit to transfer the property. For tenants in common, the decedent’s interest in the real estate will pass through probate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;TRANSFER ON DEATH (TOD) DESIGNATION AFFIDAVIT: A TOD Deed is the next step after the Survivorship Deed. It names a person or people to take the real estate only after the owner(s) have died. Again, the house will not pass through probate, instead there is a simple affidavit to execute and record in the county offices where the property is located. Again, the new owner(s) of the property takes it subject to any debt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;LIVING OR REVOCABLE TRUST: Trusts were all the rage in the 1990s and early 2000s, but are less popular now. Whether or not you need one depends on your life and family circumstances and what your estate planning goals are. If your only goal is to keep assets out of probate, there are simpler and less costly ways to do that today. Most people do not need trusts, but there are some limited reasons why a trust might be recommended. If you have a special needs beneficiary, or a beneficiary who is irresponsible with money or in a lot of debt, if you have a particular person you don’t want to have access to your estate at all, you own a family business, or you have minor children who stand to inherit a sizable estate, then you should probably at least consider a Trust. You are generally named as your own Trustee, with a Successor Trustee named if you either pass away or need to step down. The Trust must also be funded, which means that some or all of your titled property must be transferred into the name of the Trust. At the time of your death, your revocable Trust becomes irrevocable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A WORD ABOUT PROBATE AVOIDANCE&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most people shudder when they think about probate. It scares them and puts a bad taste in their mouth. While it is a complex area of law with often confusing procedures, probate is really not a dirty word.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes probate is necessary or desirable. If you are concerned about your relatives fighting over your estate, or you have complex assets that need to be treated in a particular way, court oversight can be helpful to make sure your loved ones behave themselves and the estate is managed properly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, probate can be costly and time-consuming. If you do not anticipate this sort of problem, then you can avoid it. For real property, the Joint and Survivorship Deed and the Transfer on Death Designation Affidavit discussed above will keep your home out of probate. It is worth noting that the cost of probating an estate depends on the estate’s value. Since real estate is very often a person’s most valuable asset, removing it from the probate process reduces the cost of probate considerably, even if you do nothing else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vehicles, bank accounts and investments can also be set up to avoid probate, and for these things, you do not need an attorney. Under Ohio law, surviving spouses are automatically entitled to up to two vehicles without probate, but if there is no spouse, or you want someone else to have your vehicle, you can go to the title bureau and request a new title which names either a Transfer on Death designee, or a current joint owner. If you opt for a current joint owner who is not a spouse, it is important to include the designation “WROS,” which stands for “With Rights of Survivorship.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bank accounts, CDs, Money Market accounts, and other types of investments, including stocks and bonds, should have either a current joint owner, or a named Payable on Death beneficiary on the account, which you can request at any time. Life insurance, annuities, and other select assets cannot (or should not) be opened without naming beneficiaries right from the start.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, what is the difference between a “Joint Owner” and a “Transfer/Payable on Death” beneficiary? Very simply put, a Joint Owner has a legal ownership interest in the asset immediately, while you are still living. A Transfer or Payable on Death beneficiary has NO legal interest whatsoever until AFTER you pass away.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Part 2 of a 4-part series</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">I don’t need an estate plan, do I?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2017/08/09/I-dont-need-an-estate-plan-do-i.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="I don't need an estate plan, do I?" /><published>2017-08-09T20:51:31-04:00</published><updated>2017-08-09T20:51:31-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2017/08/09/I-dont-need-an-estate-plan-do-i</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2017/08/09/I-dont-need-an-estate-plan-do-i.html">&lt;p&gt;Part 1 of a 4-part series&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What legal task do most people procrastinate on doing? Preparing an estate plan. According to an April 2016 article in USA Today[1], Prince died without a will. So did Amy Winehouse, Bob Marley, Sonny Bono, Jimi Hendrix, and Kurt Cobain. Some of these people were young – in their late 20s. Others were older – Bono was 62 – but age has little to do with the need for an estate plan. And neither does the size of your estate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is the possible result of not having an estate plan? In the cases of both Hendrix and Marley, their families each fought over the estates in the courts for more than 30 years, according to the same article. You may not have a celebrity-sized estate, but that doesn’t mean you don’t need an estate plan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Preparing an estate plan is one of the simplest, least costly things you can do to do to protect your assets and give yourself and your family peace of mind. So why not just do it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most people just don’t want to think about it. It’s morbid. It reminds them of their own mortality. It’s distasteful. They are concerned about what their loved ones might think. They are worried about “that one family member” who will object and cause problems. They have an especially irresponsible family member, or someone with special needs. They believe their loved ones will fight over the estate. They don’t trust anyone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are a million and one excuses. But I can tell you that without exception, every estate plan client who has come to me wringing their hands, has left with documents that serve their needs and those of their families. Why? Because I specialize in digging into details that many clients may not even think to mention. I design a customized estate plan just for them. Then I watch the worry lines disappear from their faces, and hear them say they can now sleep better at night.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can also tell you that those family issues, if they are to occur at all, will occur whether you have an estate plan or not. In fact, having an estate plan can help prevent some of those problems. If your estate plan is designed to include court oversight, the court can help keep your family members in line and make sure each beneficiary gets what you want them to have, nothing more and nothing less.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And if you do not anticipate any of those problems and do not need court oversight, then at least you have specific instructions in place so your loved ones do not have to play a guessing game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;NEXT: Estate plan basics. What are the parts of an estate plan and what do they do for you?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[1] Mandell, A., &amp;amp; Blas, L. (2016, April 26). 6 celebrities who died without wills. Retrieved July 6, 2017, from https://www.usatoday.com/story/life/people/2016/04/26/6-legendary-stars-who-died-without-wills/83550424/&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Part 1 of a 4-part series</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">What I’ve learned from three years of solo practice</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2017/07/10/what-ive-learned-from-three-years-of-solo-practice.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What I’ve learned from three years of solo practice" /><published>2017-07-10T20:51:31-04:00</published><updated>2017-07-10T20:51:31-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2017/07/10/what-ive-learned-from-three-years-of-solo-practice</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2017/07/10/what-ive-learned-from-three-years-of-solo-practice.html">&lt;p&gt;I came to the practice of law late. How late, we won’t say, but let’s just say it wasn’t my first career. I’ve been practicing since December 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I came up in the corporate world. I started in the printing and graphic arts field, took a break to teach for a few years, then went back to printing in a corporate setting. I loved the work, hated the environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was on a rigid schedule, I was ruled and proceedured to death, I had to be careful about working “against company policy.” I felt micro-managed and I hated the internal politics of most corporate settings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The upside was the responsibilities that I earned, and by extension, the learning opportunities that came with those responsibilities. I learned how to supervise others, how to run a production floor, how to schedule work, how to deal with all manner of clients for all manner of reasons, how to market products and services. I learned how to make and manage a budget, how to choose the best vendors, and how to make sure the bills got paid on time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that led to my deciding even before I started law school that I would be a solo practitioner. I would never, ever go back to the corporate world. I never had one single thought about joining a law firm, even a small one. I knew how to run a business so it should be easy, right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it wasn’t. I found out it’s easy to run a business on someone else’s dime while you earn a regular paycheck for the privilege. Not so much when it’s your own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was lucky enough to find a mentor who practiced in the exact same areas I was interested in. When she moved on to greener pastures in January 2016, it was easy to slip in and take over the client list. I saw her entire open case list through to completion. In the meantime, I also started with some new clients of my own. My mentor remained available for advice and answers on legal matters that I hadn’t seen before. I also inherited her assistant, whom I adored and who knew more about procedure than I did, and I grew to depend on her entirely too much.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The work got out, the billable hours piled up, and the fees rolled in. I made a good living in 2016. And I loved it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But after the first year, the cases dried up. I hadn’t done any marketing because I was so busy I almost didn’t want new clients for fear of not being able to handle the workload. I had heard that word of mouth is one of the best ways for attorneys to acquire new clients. All my clients told me they were happy with my services, that they liked the way I related to them, and they would happily refer me to their friends, but it wasn’t happening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In spite of the good reviews, by May 2017 it became apparent that I was not going to be able to sustain my outside office any longer. So I closed it up and moved home, and cut nearly $40,000 a year out of my overhead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what have I learned? I still love the work, BUT I’ve had to make changes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;CUT COSTS. My father taught me that if you want to see better profits, you cut costs. You don’t spend more money on things that may or may not work to increase your business, instead you get rid of things that weigh you down. If you cut $1K out of your cost to produce something, that’s another $1K in your pocket. Rent and payroll are the biggest expense of an outside office, and must be paid first. If you can’t manage those, you need to lose the outside office.
WATCH YOUR CASH FLOW. It’s easy to go out to lunch every day, but little costs like that add up and kill your cash flow. Watch the daily income and outgo. And take out a business line of credit for the lean times. I resisted this until I couldn’t resist it anymore, and it has been a lifesaver more than once. Don’t use it indiscriminately, don’t max it out, and pay it off ASAP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MARKET, MARKET, MARKET. There are lots of ways to market, even though attorneys are restricted by the Professional Code of Ethics. Many attorneys advertise in magazines or newspapers, and most attorneys have websites. I am creating as big an online presence as I can manage. I have a box full of pens with my name on them, and some neat looking little pads. I’m also debating some print advertising this fall. And let’s not forget word of mouth.
NETWORK. I hate networking. It suggests standing around at some social event where you don’t know anyone, making small talk you don’t care about with people who can’t help you. But it doesn’t have to be that way. I opted to join a networking group, which paid for itself after one referral. I also go to small group meetings with other attorneys who share my interests.
GET ON REFERRAL LISTS. Every local bar association has one. I’ve only been on my local bar’s referral list for about six weeks and I’ve already gotten five referrals. Not every referral will turn into an actual paid matter, but if you get one, that’s a start.
KEEP YOUR NAME IN FRONT OF YOUR EXISTING CLIENTS. Keep excellent records, and devote some hands-on time and expense. Holiday cards, thank you cards, birthday cards, happy sunny day cards. It doesn’t matter. It shows the client you’re thinking about them, you want to help them, and you’re available with a simple phone call.
STAY ORGANIZED. I always thought of myself as organized. My assistant was the most uber-organized person I’ve ever worked with in my life. I don’t know what I’m going to do without her. But I will manage. Probably not to her level of efficiency, but I’ll get it done.
STAY ON SCHEDULE. Have regular work hours and regular home hours. Don’t mix the two. This is especially difficult if you work from home. It’s tempting to go work on that file late in the evening just because it’s sitting there. It’s also tempting to deal with household obligations because they are a distraction in your face and you just want them done. Self-discipline is the key.
BE PREPARED TO WORK A LOT OF HOURS. Assistants make work hours easy. You don’t realize how much clerical work they take off your plate until you have to do it yourself.
Now the question is, where will I be a year from now? I’ll keep you posted.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I came to the practice of law late. How late, we won’t say, but let’s just say it wasn’t my first career. I’ve been practicing since December 2013.</summary></entry></feed>